HENRY M. PACHTER (HEINZ PAECHTER) PAPERS, (GER-071), 1907-1987
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Henry M. Pachter (Heinz Paechter) Papers 1907-1987
8.49 cu. ft.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
The collection contains Pachter’s writings in history, economics, current events, the social sciences and other topics. The bulk of the collection consists of Pachter’s published essayistic writings, both for journals (including numerous articles for Dissent) and for newspapers.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The Henry M. Pachter Papers were donated to the University Libraries of the State University of New York by his widow, Hedwig Pachter, beginning in January 1982.
Biographical Sketch
Henry M. Pachter was born Heinz Maximilian Paechter on January 22, 1907 in Berlin, Germany. With the exception of a year at the University of Freiburg im Breisgau, Pachter received his formal education in Berlin and graduated from the University of Berlin in 1930, with a degree in history.
During his early years, Pachter became involved in the German youth movement and was a member of Der schwarze Haufen, but his socialist leanings soon led him to become disenchanted with the elitist nature of the group. By December of 1933, his association with socialist youth groups as well as publications in an underground leftist weekly, forced him to emigrate to the safety of Paris, where he remained for the next seven years. His future wife, Hedwig Rösler, whom he had met in 1928 in Berlin, joined Pachter in Paris in 1936. In France, Pachter became as a member of the Universitaire Populaire, often wrote under the pseudonym of Henri Rabasseire (Espagne Creuset Politique, 1938), and continued his association with both French and Spanish socialists. In September 1939, Pachter was interned in France, and began efforts to immigrate to the United States. Finally, having married Hedwig in 1940, they fled over the Pyrenees into Spain and eventually sailed from Portugal, arriving together in New York in April 1941.
Pachter quickly set about mastering the English language. During the early years in the United States Pachter worked as a consultant for both the Office of War Information (OWI) and the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), while still publishing articles in German as a U.S. correspondent for German newspapers and magazines, including the Deutsche Zeitung, Der Monat and Die Weltwoche. In 1945, he became editor of Economic Trends, where he continued until 1950.
In 1952, Pachter joined the History Department of the New School for Social Research as a lecturer, rose to professor and eventually chairman of the department. Pachter remained at the New School until 1967, and even served from 1963-1964 as acting director. In later years, Pachter also taught courses at Columbia University, the City College of the City University of New York and at Rutgers University in New Jersey.
Over the years, Pachter published hundreds of essays, as well as several full-length works on a broad range of subjects in history, economics and the social sciences. His main interest, as a proclaimed liberal social democrat and an avid anti-communist, was in explaining the meaning of socialism, in defense of the morality of socialism.
Henry Pachter died in New York on December 10, 1980.
Chronology of Events
1907 Born Heinz Maximilian Paechter on January 22 in Berlin, Germany; father Emil Paechter, mother, Helene Streisand Paechter. Belonged to Der schwarze Haufen, a German youth group.
1925-1926 Attended University of Freiburg im Breisgau, where he studied under Husserl and met Hannah Arendt, with whom he maintained a lifelong friendship.
1926-1930 Returned to Berlin; attended University of Berlin; also took classes from Karl Korsch at the Marxistische Arbeiterschule.
1930 Received his Ph. D. from the University of Berlin; joined the SPD (Socialist Party).
1930-1933 Worked as a free-lance writer and lectured at the Volks-Hochschule in Berlin.
1933-1940 Lived in Paris; member of Universitaire Populaire, Paris; active in the French resistance movement against Hitler; often published under the pseudonym Henri Rabasseire.
1936 Joined by Hedwig Rösler in Paris.
1939 Publication of book on the Spanish Civil War: Espagne Creuset Politique under the pseudonym Henri Rabasseire; interned briefly in France.
1940 Married Hedwig Rösler; fled France, travelling over the Pyrenees to Spain and eventually Portugal.
1941 April, emigrated to the United States on emergency visa.
1941-1945 Became a consultant for the Office of War Information (OWI); research associate for the Office of European Economic Research of the Office of Strategic Services (OSS).
1943 Birth of daughter Renée Vera.
1945-1950 Editor of Economic Trends.
1948 Became naturalized U.S. citizen.
1948-1964 Became U.S. correspondent for German newspapers, Deutsche Zeitung (Cologne), Der Monat (Berlin), Weltwoche (Zurich).
1951 Awarded Guggenheim grant for his work on recent changes in the social status of the intelligentsia, written for the Deutsche Zeitung.
1952-1967 Began as lecturer; became professor and chair of the Dept. of History, New School for Social Research.
1954 Became regular contributor to Dissent magazine; eventually co-editor.
1963-1964 Acting Dean of the New School for Social Research.
1965 Visiting professor at Columbia University.
1967-1976 Visiting Professor of History, City College of City University of New York.
1977-1980 Co-adjunct in political science at University College, Rutgers University.
1980 Died on December 10 in New York City.
Scope and Content Information
The Henry M. Pachter Papers contains Pachter’s writings in history, economics, current events, the social sciences and other topics. The bulk of the collection consists of Pachter’s published essayistic writings, both for journals (including numerous articles for Dissent) and for newspapers. Also included are typescripts of two posthumously published full-length works, including his autobiography, Weimar Études. Typescript versions of several earlier autobiographical sketches, both in English and in German, as well as biographical tapes, are also present.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, 1907-1980, Undated
Series 2 - Manuscripts and Typescripts of Essayistic Writings, 1951-1980, Undated
Series 3 - Reviews of Pachter's Books, 1938-1984, Undated
Series 4 - Full-Length Works by Pachter and Others, 1982-1984, Undated
Series 5 - Articles Published in Journals, 1929-1987, Undated
Series 6 - Published Newspaper Articles, 1919-1980, Undated
Series 7 - Audio Tapes, Oversized Materials, 1984, Undated
Subject and Genre Headings
Pachter, Henry Maximilian, 1907-; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Economics--Study and teaching.; History--Study and teaching.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Germans--United States.; Jews--Germany--Berlin.; New York (N.Y.); Correspondence; Autobiographies; Reviews (document genre); Essays; Typescripts; Articles; Clippings; Photographs
Container List
- Series 1: Biographical and Autobiographical Materials, 1907-1980; Undated
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains autobiographical essays by Pachter, both in manuscript and published form, as well as writings about Pachter, including memorials by colleagues after his death in 1980. Also included in this series is a small amount of correspondence dealing with employment, and a few letters from contemporaries, including Thomas Mann and Martin Jay.
  - Documents, 1907-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, list of publications, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (2) of Pachter, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book lists from Pachter’s personal library, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Articles about Pachter, including lexicon and memorial articles, 1952-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence re: appointments, 1952-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, incl. L. from Martin Jay (1), Fritz Lamm, Thomas Mann (1), 1950s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - “Men in the Camp.” Typescript, ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - “April 1941, on board the Nyassa.” Typescript (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - “A dream, Jan. 1946.” Typescript, pc. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - “17. Juni 1953.” Handwritten and typescript versions (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - “16. Juli 1953. Tagebuch einer Heimkehr.” Typescripts. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - “Schmerzliches Wiedersehen mit Berlin.” Clipping., ca. 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - “Über den Tod. Fragmente.” Handwritten and typewritten versions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - “Zorniger alter Herr nimmt Abschied vom Journalismus.” Clipping., 28. Jan. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - “Growing Up Jewish in Weimar Germany.” Clipping, June 29, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Manuscripts and Typescripts of Essayistic Writings, 1951-1980; Undated
  Arranged by language (German, then English) and alphabetically within languages.
  This series consists of typescript and manuscript versions of Pachter’s essayistic writings, many unpublished.
  - "Ich melde mich zum Wort. Offener Brief an Hermann Kesten.” Typescript, unpub, Feb. 17, 1964. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - “’John L.’ Macht stets Geschichte.” Typescript, unpub, Oct. 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - “Juden und Neger.” Typescript, unpub, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - “Kafka-tisch.” Handwritten and typed versions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - “Kulturpolitik – Unkultur der Politik versus Politik der Unkultur. Typescript, unpub, ca. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - “Die Kunst dem Volke – auch in Amerika.” Typescript, unpub, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - “Meinecke.” Typescript, unpub, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - “Mitbestimmungsrecht und Produktionskontrolle in Amerika.” Typescript, unpub, ca. 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - “Sozialismus in Amerika.” Typescript, unpub, June 14, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - “Ueber das Problem der Zeit.” Typescript, unpub, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Untitled handwritten and typed fragments, in German and English, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - “A Letter to Some Jewish Friends.” Typescript, ca. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - “A Memoir of Walter Benjamin.” Handwritten and typewritten versions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - “A Proposal to Surrender.” Typescript, photocopy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - “An ‘Inauthentic Jew’s Reply to Jean-Paul-Sartre.” Typescripts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - “Banausos Talks Back – A Project.” Typescript, photocopy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - “Bonn Is Not Weimar.” Typescript, photocopy, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - “Café Groessenwahn.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - “Can the Holocaust Be A Bore?” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - “Chomsky in His Bailiwick.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - “Does Marxism Need a Foundation in Philosophy. Typescript, photocopy, Nov. 16, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - “Dreyfus Reviewed.” Typescript, Dec. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - “Erich Muehsam 1872-1934-1978.” Typescript (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - “History and Nature.” Handwritten, Undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - “History and Time.” Typescript, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - “In Memoriam Jacob Blauner.” Typescript, photocopy, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - “Isaac Newton 1642-1727.” Typescript with notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - “Jews in German Literature.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - “Joseph Borkin, the Crime and Punishment of I.G. Farben.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - “The Left in World Politics.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - “The Much-Overdue Rehabilitation of Karl Kautsky, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - “The Near East Crisis.” Typescript, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - “On an Essay of Meyer Shapiro.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - “Politics, Values, and Political Science.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - “The Realm of Thought.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - “Realpolitik, Machtpolitik.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - “The Rejection-Reflection Syndrome in Expressionism.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - “Socialism and Democracy – Complementary or Contradictory?” Handwritten and typed, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - “Soviet Power in the Middle East, Israel, and the Jews.” Typescript, Nov. 1967 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - “Spain Revisited: Superficial Aspects of a Revolution.” Typescript, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - “Terrorism and Legitimacy – Bonn and Weimar.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - “Theory and Praxis – Observations on the work of Juergen Habermas.” Typescript, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - “Thirty Years Old – And in Berlin.” Typescript, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - “Toward a Marxist Theory of the State.” Typescript, photocopy, Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - “Vigilantism in Germany and Austria during the 1920s.” Typescripts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Unpublished reviews. Typescript, photocopy, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- Series 3: Reviews of Pachter's Books, 1938-1984; Undated
  This series contains reviews of eleven of Pachter’s full-length works, including his early work written and published in French on the Spanish Civil War, Espagne Creuset Politique (1938), works in German and in English published after his emigration to the United States, as well as two volumes published posthumously, an autobiography Weimar Études (1982) and an essay volume Socialism in History (1984).
  - Espagne Creuset Politique, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - The Axis Grand Strategy, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Nazi Deutsch, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Paracelsus. Magic into Science. Reviews, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Paracelsus. Magic into Science. Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - The Third Reich, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Chruschtschow – Kennedy – Castro, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - The Cuban Missile Crisis and Coexistence, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Weltmacht Rußland, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Modern Germany, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Weimar Études, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Socialism in History, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Series 4: Full-Length Works by Pachter and Others, 1982-1984; Undated
  Arranged by work.
  Included in this series are two works published posthumously, Weimar Études and Socialism in History, as well as a second planned essay volume, History and Myth, edited by Stephen Eric Bronner, which remains unpublished. Also included in this series are typescripts and proofs of the translation by Hedwig Pachter of Hermann Vinke’s The Short Life of Sophie Scholl.
  - Socialism in History. Correspondence, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Socialism in History. Proofs, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 76-77)
  - Socialism in History. Parts I-II. Typescripts, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Socialism in History. Parts III-IV. Typescripts, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Socialism in History. Photographs used in the volume, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Weimar Études. Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Weimar Études. “Memoirs, first Ms.” Handwritten, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Weimar Études. Early handwritten and typed versions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Weimar Études. Introduction. Typescript, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Weimar Études. Typescripts, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Weimar Études. Page proofs, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Vinke, Hermann. The Short Life of Sophie Scholl. Translation by Hedwig Pachter. Typescripts, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Vinke, Hermann. The Short Life of Sophie Scholl. Proofs, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
  - Vinke, Hermann. The Short Life of Sophie Scholl. Unbound copy, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Oppens, Kurt. “Emily Dickinson: Überlieferung und Prophete.” Proofs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - History and Myth. Planned volume of essays by Pachter, edited by Stephen Eric Bronner. Typescripts, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Series 5: Articles Published in Journals, 1929-1987; Undated
  Arranged chronologically in German and English.
  This series contains copies of the essayistic writings of Pachter published in journals or as sections in books. Most are in published form, with a few accompanied by typescript versions. Also included in this section are Pachter’s book and film reviews.
  - “Hände weg von Russland – Hände weg von China!” Photocopy, July 19, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - “Der revolutionäre Internationalismus und der ‘Renegat’ Trotzky.” Photocopy, Nov./Dec. 1929 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - “Kommunismus und Klasse.” Photocopy, Oct. 1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - “State and Nation in the Spanish War.” Photocopy, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - “Reflections on the Spanish Civil War.” Photocopy, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - “Recent Trends in the German Command Economy.” Clipping, Sept. 1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - “Washington, den 25. Mai 1946.” Photocopy, June 15, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - “Ike, Adlai und die Parteibosse.” Clipping, Oct. 1952 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - “Der Schmelztiegel arbeitet langsam.”Clipping, Jan. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - “Hundert Jahre nach ‘Onkel Toms Hütte’.” Clipping, Feb. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - “Die neuen Männer in Washington.” Clipping, Mar. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - “Der letzte Jakobiner. Sozialismus war für Paul Fröhlich eine Idee und keine Taktik.” Typescript, Mar. 28, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - “Reporter des Nichts.” Clipping, Apr. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - “Die Heimkehr des ‘entfremdeten’ Sohnes.” Clipping, July 1, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - “Angst als politische Mach.” Clipping, Sept./Oct. 1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - “And Can There Be Peace?...” Clipping, Summer 1954 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - “Der ‘böse Friedrich’ geht um.” Clipping, Dec. 1954 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - “Fascist Propaganda and the Conquest of Power.” Photocopy, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - “McCarthy und die Katholiken.” Clipping, Mar./Apr. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - “McCarthy und die Katholiken.” Clipping, Winter 1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - “Der Fall Matthias.” Clipping, Feb. 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - “Die Heiligen Rollen vom Toten Meer.” Clipping, Feb. 1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - “Some Aspects of Mass Culture.” Alternate title: “In Defense of Television.” Clipping, Summer 1956 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - “Amerikanische Gewerkschaften vor der Wahl.”, July/Aug 1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - “Atomabrüstung und Atomdiplomatie.” Clipping, Nov 1957 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - “Confessions of an Old-Timer.” Photocopy, Winter 1958 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - “A Bewildering Debate.” Clipping, Spring 1958 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - “Leisure – the Wealth of man: Henri Rabasseire replies:” Clipping, Spring 1958 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - “The Pattern of Sociological Theory.” Clipping, Fall 1958 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - “Foreign Policy: a Revolutionary Alternative: Henry Pachter replies:” Clipping, Winter 1959 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - “The Pope … and the Papers.” Clipping, Jan. 1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - “Politics and Economics in Southeast Asia.” Clipping, Fall 1959 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - “Changes in the Communist World: A Critical Comment.” Clipping, Spring 1959 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Vigilanten und Dinosaurier.” Clipping, April 1959 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - “Die Verheissung bleibt ihnen lebendig.” Clipping, October 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - “Co-Existence Revisited.” Clipping, October 1959 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - “Paradoxes of Foreign Aid.” Clipping, June 1960 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - “The Meaning of ‘Peaceful Coexistence’.” Clipping, Jan/Feb 1961 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - “A Foreign Policy.” Clipping, Winter 1961 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - “Yankee no.” Clipping, February 1961 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - “Koexistenz als Idee und Strategie.” Clipping, March 1961 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - “Rätselhafte Revolution.” Clipping, April 1961 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - “Forschungs-Manager und Staats-Manager.” Clipping, May 1961 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - “In Washington nichts Neues.” Clipping, June 1961 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - “Germany Looks in the Mirror of History.” Clipping, July 1961 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - “Kennedy nach Kuba und Wien.” Clipping, July 1961 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - “The G.S.” Clipping, Fall 1961 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - “The So-called Berlin Question.” Clipping, Fall 1961 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - “George Kennan: The Perils of History.” Clipping, Fall 1961 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - “Die Negerfrage ist keine ökonomische Frage.” Clipping, Oct. 1961 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - “Amerikas ‘neuer’ Neger.” Clipping, Dec. 1961 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - “Radikalismus in den USA.” Clipping, Feb 1962 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - “The Legend of the 20th of July 1944.” Clipping, Spring 1962 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - “Vereinte Nationen – Uneinige Regierungen.” Clipping, Mar./Apr. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - “Radikalismus in den USA.” Clipping, Apr. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - “Wie Kennedy regiert.” Clipping, Aug. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Abolishing the Octopus.” Clipping. Fall, Fall 1962 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - “Polarisierung der Weltpolitik.” Clipping, Dec. 1962 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - “Amerikas Republikaner.” Clipping, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - "Collective Guilt Disputed.” Clipping, ca. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - “Der Ost-West-Konflikt.” Issue, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - “Amateur Diplomats and the Peace Literature.” Clipping, Spring 1963 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - “The U.N.’s 17th Assembly.” Clipping, Winter 1963 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - “Amateur Diplomats and the Peace Literature.” Clipping, Spring 1963 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - “Popes and Communists.” Clipping, June 1963 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - “Taking Issue With ‘Armegeddon’.” Clipping, Summer 1963 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - “Cuba Discussion.” Clipping, Summer 1963 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - “Automatisierung in Amerika.” Clipping, July/Aug. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - “Rassenstreit als Verfassungskampf.” Clipping, July/Aug. 1963 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - “Amerika, ein Produkt des 18. Jahrhunderts.” Clipping, Sept 1963 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - “Kapitalistische und Wohlfahrtsplanung in Amerika.” Clipping, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - “The Best of all Social Democracies?” Clipping, Winter 1964 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - “Verhandeln ohne Illusionen.” Clipping, Feb 1964 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - “Capitalism, the Welfare State, and Socialism.” Issue, clipping, Spring 1964 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - “Weisheit oder Ratlosigkeit?” Clipping, April 1964 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - “Johnsons Dilemma.” Clipping, July/Aug. 1964 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - “Die ersten beiden Jahre Johnsons.” Issue, 1964/1965 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - “Das Ost-West-Verhältnis und die amerikanischen Interventionen in der Dominikanischen Republik und Vietnam.” Issue., 1964/1965 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - “Von Roosevelt bis Kennedy.” Clipping, Feb. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - “Vietnam and the Left.” Typescript, clipping, Fall 1965 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - “JFK as an Equestrian Statue: On Myth and Mythmakers.” Clipping, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - “Die Kluft weitet sich. Schwarze und Weiße in den USA.” Clipping, Jan/Feb 1966 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - “Johnsons zwei Kriege.” Clipping, Feb 1966 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - “’Neuer’ Linksradikalismus in den USA.” Clipping, Apr 1966 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - “Uses and Abuses of Civil Disobedience.” Clipping, May/June 1966 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - “Die UNO und die deutsche Frage.”Clipping, Sept/Oct 1966 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - “Marxism and America’s New Left.” Clipping, Jan 1967 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - “Let’s Talk Sense About Oswald.” Clipping, Mar/Apr 1967 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - “Lessons of Middle East Crisis.”Clipping, June 18, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - “Troubles of a Jewish Conscience.” Clipping, July 1967 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - “Chinas Vertretung in den Vereinten Nationen.” Clipping, Aug 1967 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - “Das Deutschlandbild der Amerikaner.” Clipping, Sept/Oct 1967 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - “Zur Einführung” [Weltmacht Rußland]. Clipping, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - “Notes on the Soviet Union.” Photocopy, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 96)